foreign
[Music]
so let's get this show on the road
welcome everybody to the speedrun game
last couple games have been really
instructive like really instructive
so we're riding a pretty good streak
those watching on YouTube welcome
to you as well I want to thank everybody
who subscribes and supports the channel
we're very very close to 300K Subs
which is a big milestone for me so the
best way to support the channel if you
like the content you like what I do is
just to hit the Subscribe button all
right we're playing an 11 40 with the
white pieces
and we continue to play my sort of
official opening recommendations and we
are facing the French defense okay
so those of you who've watched my speed
run more assiduously you will probably
remember what my official recommendation
is against the French and this is a very
dangerous line that hits a couple of
different
uh targets at once on the one hand it's
very dangerous from a theoretical
standpoint if black is not careful then
white can get a big objective Advantage
but this line also teaches you a lot
about closed structures and a lot about
positional chess in general so it's
always good to have a line like this in
your pocket that basically forces you to
display your knowledge of certain
typical structures in certain uh
important positional ideas and the line
that I'm alluding to is not the tarash
which I play at my level I play the move
Knight to D2 but a line that I have also
played over the board and I think the
official name for it is the nimsovich
French it starts just like an advanced
French we start by playing the move E5
this is the advance and black response
with C5 so this is standard fare and
here the move which is almost automatic
for most people is of course to support
the pawn Chain by pushing C3 and that
leads to uh very theoretical Waters the
advanced French
is a totally viable weapon and it's
gained a lot of popularity in recent
years so even at you know super high
level but the line that has slipped
through the cracks is actually to play
this without C3 and instead to develop
your pieces as if nothing is the matter
so the NIMS of its French goes Knight to
F3 we simply develop our Knight and we
allow black
to ruin our Pawn Chain by playing C
takes D4
so you can go back through the first
Speed Run and look at a couple of games
in which I played this line I will do a
quick overview of the basic ideas once
again in case this is the first time
that you're seeing the move Knight F3 if
it is the first time you're seeing
Knight F3 then you should be very very
surprised because it seems utterly
counter-intuitive uh to allow the pawn
chain to be destroyed let alone to
sacrifice the pawn on D4 which is what
we're gonna do and here we continue
playing as though black is not exerting
any pressure on D4 we continue
developing our pieces now people who are
less experienced in the French one
common mistake that I see players making
uh is that they play no not Bishop B6
but Bishop B5 in this position is a very
common move at the beginner level that
is not a good move the bishop on B5 is
not futile and it's not bad because it
loses a piece it doesn't lose a piece
Queen A5 check there is Knight C3
so it's bad from a conceptual standpoint
the bishop on B5 is a total paper tiger
and blackened just block the pin with
Bishop D7
so the best Square in such positions for
White's bishop and we're going to deploy
the bishop to that score right now
is actually D3
and there's many reasons for that
anytime you have you know a Pawn on D4
like this putting the bishop behind the
pawn is good practice
in case black Castle's King side which
is the likeliest direction the black
will eventually Castle we will have a
Greek gift sacrifice at the ready but I
hear the thought that's on your mind
doesn't black just have C4 pushing the
bishop back to E2 well they do but we
have provoked C4 and because the center
is relatively closed we can afford in
such positions to make more than one
move with the same piece so what is
white achieved by provoking the move C4
well a couple of very specific things
first of all we've taken a lot of the
pressure off of the D4 Pawn we no longer
have to worry about our Pawn chain
getting destroyed so we can instead
focus on more important things like
quickly completing our King side
development now Black's Pawn chain on
the queen side might seem very imposing
and the move B5 is actually good but in
fact black has bitten off a lot more
than she can chew okay and the reason
for that is that black is pushing all of
their pawns on the queen side without
supporting them with his or her pieces
and what we can do is use our Pawns in a
kind of very typical idea to break down
the entire Pawn chain the black is
building up on the queen side and the
way that we do that is by putting
pressure simultaneously on both the C4
Pawn as well as the B5 pawn and we have
both pawns that can do that we play the
move B3 setting up pressure on the C4
pawn and we follow up with the move A4 a
very very important Motif this is kind
of classic Pawn play to break down
Black's Pawn chain as quickly as
possible and we can do it without delay
we can Castle
we can take a move and complete our King
side development but we don't even need
to do that we can just straight up play
A4 in this position and black is already
under very serious fire on the queen
side and one important tactical detail
that you should notice is that A6 is
futile here because of a takes B5 and
black cannot recapture with the a pawn
because the Rook on a it hangs so that's
part of the reason it's important to do
this in timely fashion if we had a loud
black to play the move Bishop to B7
which is not played to develop the
bishop to an active Square it's played
in order to defend the Rook A4 while
still a pretty decent move is a lot less
effective on account of A6 that move is
now possible
so here this is rather time sensitive
and with the Rook on Aid on defended A4
is a very powerful move
Bishop A6 so our opponent
conceptually is playing reasonably
uh he or she is trying to protect the
pawn chain with uh the pieces with the
minor pieces but it's not going to work
because the minor pieces are just not
very good at keeping the pawn chain
intact and even though black isn't going
to avoid losing pawns immediately we're
still gonna break up the pawn chain so
which Pawn should we take first Well
normally we should begin by eliminating
the base of the pawn chain
step one is to play a takes B5
eliminating the kind of linchpin on B5
now step two would of course be to then
take the pawn on C4 opening up the
center and creating a major weakness on
C4 as a result
now we can also kind of ignore the
situation and we can just Castle but far
more to the point and far more kind of
consecutive is to play the move B take
C4 and as a result of the trade black is
going to get a massive weakness on C4
Bishop takes C4 and now of course we
complete the trade with Bishop takes C4
and after d takes C4 we have achieved
precisely what we set about to do on the
queen side we have created long-term
permanent weaknesses on the queen side
what are those weaknesses well the main
weakness is this Pawn on C4 and step
three is going to involve two kind of
mini steps we need to complete our
development it's going to be hard for us
to operate to our full capacity without
castling and without solidifying our own
punching how are we going to solidify
our Pawn chain what move comes to mind
here as kind of an automatic move if
you're a French player with white
what is kind of the general solidifying
move that we're going to play at some
point yeah that's the move
scene now you might say well wait a
second
Square shouldn't that be reserved for
the night no the Knight isn't doesn't go
to C3 in such positions it's gonna go
out to D2 because remember the ultimate
idea uh is to harass and ultimately win
the C4 Pawn
so what's going to be the order of
operations here well we can do things in
a bunch of different orders I like the
idea what appeals to me is just castling
kingside first just to get the king out
of the danger zone make sure that there
are no nasty checks on B4 then after
that to play the move C3
and only after those two preliminary
steps are complete can we go about the
process of surrounding and winning the
C4 Pawn so castling first is safe
because black has no good way to attack
the D4 Pawn Rook d8 is a very likely
move at this level and just in time we
follow up with the move C3 notice also
in that position that Knight takes E5 is
not possible because the Knight on F3
guards the E5 font so our opponent is
trying to open up the center which is a
counterproductive idea because black is
lacking in development and this is an
important moment for me to highlight the
idea of flexibility right we created
this entire elaborate scheme where we
were gonna go C3 and then we were gonna
go Knight bd2 but Black's last move has
changed absolutely everything F6 is a
huge move and we need to understand how
that impacts our course of action well
it changes our course of action entirely
because black is inviting us to open up
the center
now who benefits in the event that the
Center opens up well the site that's
better developed in the side with less
Pawn weaknesses and clearly in both
cases that's white so we should actually
welcome the opening of the center
and we should do that just by taking on
F6 and saying you want to open up the
Center thank you very much I'm going to
open up the center and I'm more
precisely I'm going to open up the
e-file on which sits a massive Pawn
weakness on E6 now combining the two
previous observations right there are
two big weaknesses in Black's Camp the
pawn on E6 the newly created weakness
but nothing happened to the old weakness
of C4 so putting those two things
together generates for us the move Queen
to E2 hitting both of these pawns at
once that's the classy move
now a good alternative to Queen E2 would
be the simple rookie one we could say
hey I don't care about the C4 Pawn what
I care about more is the Pawn on E6
that's the juicy Pawn if we win that
pawn we're probably going to Checkmate
black in a matter of a couple moves
furthermore after Queen E2 as some of
you are astutely pointing out there's
the nasty move Knight takes D4
and that leads to a slightly complicated
line Knight takes D4 Knight takes D4
Queen takes D4 we grabbed the pawn on E6
with check black plays Bishop E7 and
I'm not entirely sold on the fact that
white has a crystal clear way to
capitalize on the attack there so a more
controlled move in this position would
just be to play the move rookie one
leaving the queen on a defensive spot
for now to guard the D4 Pawn and it's
incredibly hard for black to defend the
pawn on E6 that is a huge weakness and
Black's lack of development is really
costing her here as you can see because
if black had already developed the
bishop on f8
then they would be able to Castle
kingside and we would still take the
pawn on E6 but black would get a pretty
major lead in development in that case
now black just doesn't have the time to
complete the development King F7 is an
attempt to defend the pawn on E6 but
it's futile the king is not a good
defender in these kinds of positions how
should we proceed in this position
how should we proceed in this position
yeah there is a rip move
and of course that move is the simple
Fork on G5
knocking the king back to G8 the game is
not over
the game is far from over we won a pawn
but we still need to demonstrate some
good technique especially considering
the fact that we have not completed Our
Queen we haven't even started Our Queen
side development so we're gonna have to
play this accurately if we want to win
the game fast
okay so I'm anticipating King to G8 here
our opponent is playing very fast
and that's a risky thing to do in a
position with a king this wide open King
E7 whoa okay our opponent just walks
right into the pin that's a terrible
move
but how do we punish it in the most
clinical way
what's the order of operations here well
you might be tempted here by the move
Knight takes C6 to set up a potential
Discovery Knight takes C6 is okay but it
gives black
s on life Knight takes C6 allows the
king to step away from the discovery
with King F7 and then go back to G8 a
much better approach here would be to
take on E6 with the Rook but not because
it's a check right the fact that it's a
check is a nice byproduct what I'm
noticing here is that there's a pin
against the Knight on on C6 so on the
next move we can actually pre-move D5
and that ends the game on the spot
because it wins the night on C6 and once
the minor piece is gone the black king
is also getting hunted down mercilessly
here so D5 is the game-winning move and
we're gonna win this game really without
our entire Queen side we won't even need
most probably our Knight on B1 and
Bishop on C1 that's how powerful our
existing pieces are
yeah it's a little bit too late to start
thinking but you do often see this at
this level where people kind of rattle
off these opening moves and then by the
time it's too late they start thinking
yeah the game is is totally over we're
taking the Knight on the next move the
Knight cannot move because the queen is
pinned and it's going to be Checkmate in
three moves here
it's going to be Checkmate in three
moves who can give me the entire
checkmating line from start to finish
and if you're watching on YouTube try to
generate that line as well
it's a simple mating line but it's
always good practice to try to visualize
these lines in your mind it really gets
the wheels turning
without moving the queen not DC and
queen D7 the D7 square is protected by
the Knight on F6 DC is correct
and then the next move is Washington
I'm just kidding after DC King C7 what's
the mating move
I never said there's a moratorium on
bringing the queen side pieces out
Bishop F4 is the mating move very good
DC check the Knight defends The Rook
which is very important
and after King C7 The Mating move is
Bishop F4 technically black as Bishop D6
that's why it's made in three and queen
takes D6 there is Checkmate simple
straightforward attacking chess bringing
the bishop out
with a devastating check
and ending the game on the spot
yeah straightforward game
and you can see the power of the the
line that we played in the French it's
it's an incredibly powerful line
at any level I would say 2300 and under
so let's quickly go over the game
um we played
of the line that I have played
previously in the speedrun and this is
what I have played uh almost exclusively
when we faced the French in all of
across all of the speedruns I've had
thus far
so E5
is the advanced French but now we
deviate from standard Waters with the
move Knight F3
and Knight F3 has kind of an interesting
history this move has been around for a
very long time and Aaron nimsovich who
I'm sure most people watching have heard
of he is of course one of the kind of
patriarchal figures of modern positional
chess he wrote a very famous book called
my system in the 1920s which kind of
laid out a lot of the positional
Concepts that we now take for granted I
mean he was the originator of over
protection and prophylaxis and he talked
about Square control And Trades I mean
when he released my system all of these
Concepts were not in the common chess
vocabulary so people were reading that
book with their mouth kind of open like
oh my God you know this is amazing now
Knight F3 was first played in the year
let me check
it was first played in the year
1826 by an unknown player and nimsovich
was maybe the seventh or the eighth guy
to play Knight F3 but he was playing it
religiously nimsovich faced the French a
lot and he played Knight F3 exclusively
so it was pretty impressive to generate
this idea in the early 1900s and most of
nimsovich's opponents actually did not
place he takes D4
so after a c takes D4 nimsovich was the
first player to realize that the best
move in this position is not Knight
takes D4 this just defeats the purpose
of the line does that make sense Knight
takes D4
is not where the party's at black and
just go Knight C6 and this begs the
question well why on Earth didn't you
play C3 if this is how you want to play
instead white needs to aim for very
rapid development what is the actual
move after C takes D4 who can tell me
no it's not Queen takes D4 that walks
into Knight C6 even more blatantly it's
Bishop D3 good good memory Bishop D3
and the basic idea of this line
according to nimsovich is that the pod
on E5 is there's no name for this Pawn
but it's like a clamp pawn it clamps
down very effectively on Black's
position severing the connection between
the queen side and the King side making
it difficult for black to get her pieces
out effectively
in particular it prevents Knight F6 it
prevents Bishop D6 and it makes it very
difficult for black to breathe and white
is going to accelerate his his King side
development as much as possible so for
example if black just develops normally
let's say Knight C6 and we have faced
this in the speed run White Castles
and already you can see how difficult it
is for Black to develop comfortably
so if black plays let's say Bishop C5 we
are not trying to win the pawn back
quickly we're trying to win it back
eventually and the way that we're going
to do that is by putting the B1 Knight
on what Square who can tell me what
Square then that on B1 usually belongs
on in this line
so it goes to D2 but what's the final
destination
very good the Knight belongs on this
very nice B3 Square where it's out of
the way of the Bishops it's not
obstructing the Bishops that's important
and it's obviously putting pressure on
the D4 Pawn So eventually we're going to
win the pawn back
drops the bishop back to B6 and one
great thing about this line is that it
gives you a chance to carry out the
Greek gift sacrifice a ton of people end
up castling here and this loses the game
on the spot to a classic instance of the
Greek gift Bishop H7 Knight G5 check and
you know the drill King G6 Queen G4
Etc
so you can definitely win your fair
share of games in this line with a great
gift sacrifice now obviously black does
not need to fall for the Greek gifts and
if we go back to this position which is
actually in my analysis this is a
legitimate theoretical position in this
line the way the black can avoid the
Greek gift is either by delaying
castling black and play Bishop D7 or
black can situate a knight on G6 and
prevent the Bishop from taking on H7 but
at this point white can already win the
pawn back and after Bishop G6 HG knight
uh I think the move here is actually to
throw in H3 to take the sting out of
Queen H4 and according to the engine
like the engine sometimes gives a small
Edge for white and we're gonna take back
on D4 and we're gonna support the Knight
with C3 and we're gonna leave black with
this terrible French Bishop on C8 so
there's a lot of theory in this line and
black has many ways to equalize but
nonetheless there's a good amount of
meat on the bone in this line
um now I'm sure we're gonna face the
French again and we're gonna face it at
a higher level so remember the kind of
idea of the speedrun is for me to
introduce opening ideas slowly when
we're at like 12 to 1300 I'm talking
more about Concepts I'm talking about
some basic Theory and as we rise through
the ranks I'll start talking more
specifically and give you actual lines
and actual analysis
so the basic idea of this line is to
develop your king side very quickly and
make sure that whatever you do you don't
give up the pawn on E5 easily
now at a high level people who
understand the French understand that
one of Black's main weapons in these
types of positions is a move like F6
black can try to physically get rid of
the E5 Pawn but White's not giving that
pawn away easily and here white has the
very strong response Bishop B5
now you might say well wait a second
didn't I mention earlier that Bishop B5
is a misplaced Bishop in this line well
again the situation has changed
completely as a result of the move F6
and here Bishop B5 should make perfect
sense to you you're taking the sting out
of f take C5 now Knight takes E5 is
incredibly strong because you're
attacking from both sides Queen H5 is a
threat and Knight takes C6 as a threat
so Bishop B5 is a prophylactic measure
against F takes E5 okay so F6 is not a
Panacea either it's a risky move and if
black knows what what they're doing uh
then he can get away with it but in any
case our opponent took a different
approach Knight C6 Bishop D3 and our
opponent decided not to take on D4 at
all and instead to push C4 which already
gives white a sizable Advantage after
the move Bishop E2
this is already a sizable Advantage for
white according to the engine I've
analyzed this line because it's very
very common at the lower levels to push
C4
so I think B5 is a further inaccuracy I
don't think it's a terrible move but I
actually think black's main mistake
uh early in the opening was this move
Queen B6 I feel like after A4 Black's
Queen side is already collapsing and it
would not be too radical to say the
blackest borderline lost here like with
the queen side totally gone
Black's King side is undeveloped it's
plus over minus at this point so I think
the last chance for black to keep his
Queen side relatively well protected was
to play what who can tell me a decent
move for black here that allows them to
keep the queen side you know more or
less defended
and you might remember what I mentioned
about A4 and why A4 is so strong in this
position yeah Bishop B7 or maybe bishop
D7 the engine likes putting the bishop
on D7 which makes some sense it's a
little bit more centralized than the
bishop on B7
and after A4 black plays A6 and black
holds on
the queen side is still intact and then
black will try to get get you know these
King side pieces out Knight G7 Knight F5
is a very typical maneuver in the French
white is better
and from White side I wouldn't even Rush
with A4
white has this interesting move in such
positions to actually just push the
h-pawn
and your idea is to push it all the way
to H5 and maybe even to H6 to provoke
dark Square weaknesses on the king side
and the secondary idea is to prevent the
black knight from jumping into G6 which
is a super typical kind of parking spot
in these positions
furthermore you also take the sting out
of the move Knight F5 because now the
g-pawn comes to the rescue with G4 so
without the pawn on H5 if you think
about it let's make a couple of random
moves let's say white plays C3 and white
plays a developing move and black puts
them in an F5 here
the move G4 and this is very common in
the French you should remember this G4
in this version is not effective who can
tell me why what does black have in
response to G4 here that that he
wouldn't have had with the pawn already
on H5 yeah there is this very nasty move
Knight H4
and you've bitten off more than you can
chew on the king side because after the
trade you've got all of these weird kind
of weaknesses on the king side you can't
go Knight F3 this Pawn is sticking out
like a sore thumb black and go H5 later
so compared to the position after the
pawn appears on H5 here after G4 The
Rook controls H4 so the Knight is pushed
back to E7 or back to H6
so this is why closed positions are
difficult to play because they're all of
these like subtleties and everything
really does boil down to uh to nuances
and to to who can position their pieces
better who understands more ideas about
the position uh and this is a good
example of that how does Bishop D7 solve
the a takes B5 weakness asks taper
Knight well it solves the problem
because after A4 A6 the queen and the
Rook are connected so a takes B5 is no
longer effective you're not losing The
Rook on 8 you can just recapture with
the queen
and of course with the bishop still on
C8 The Rook is unprotected
so Queen B6 is a good move conceptually
our opponent understood that he needs to
protect the pawn chain on the Kings on
the queen side but forgot I would
imagine that A6 is no longer effective
with the Rook on A8 unprotected
dark Tigger asks was A4 B4 B3 that's a
man that's a mouthful a valid
continuation so I would say not as much
and the reason why consists in the move
B4 the presence of this move would make
A4 futile and now if you were to play B3
after C3 black has buried your entire
Queen side under a pile of rubble this
is a nightmare scenario because you're
never getting your night out without
sacrificing it this is what you want to
avoid and I could show you a bunch of
games like this
so and if you play C3 then black can
again try to bury you with the move B3
this is not quite as disastrous but
clearly white has not achieved anything
positive on the queen side
clearly white has not achieved any
anything positive so in this case you
actually want to fix the root of the
pawn chain first so that black can't
play B4 or run the risk of losing the C4
Pawn
so in any case Queen b6a4 Bishop A6 now
we clear the Shrubbery on the queen side
and we leave black with a massive Pawn
weakness on C4 as well as a wide open
Queen side that we can use to infiltrate
uh later on with the move Rook B1 so I
think the main theme of the middle game
was how we managed to to switch at the
drop of a hat from one plan to another
right so our initial plan which we would
have put into effect after a move like
Rook d8 was the first place E3
and then play Knight bd2 and surround
the pod on C4 which is really easy to do
because black can't defend this Pawn
if Queen B5
then the simplest move here I think is
just Queen to E2
and I should point out that black can
try to go Knight D5 and counter-attack
the C3 Pawn
but here we can kind of switch gears a
little bit and go Knight to E4
very typical Square in this particular
type of structure
and there's basically no rush to win the
pawn on C4 we can use the other Knight
and drop it back to D2
so notice how we apportion the rolls
here the Knight defense C3 and can test
the D6 Square while the other Knight is
going to drop back and win the C4 Pawn
so Black's not going to give away the
pawn that easily so if you play Knight
F22 here black micro Knight A5
but at this point we can clear off the
D6 Square another very typical idea in
the French Bishop C1 to A3 devastating
move absolutely devastating because
after the trade Knight D6 is a totally
Unstoppable idea Black's also falling
apart here on the queen side that Knight
on A5 is very poorly defended White's
gonna go Rook to B1 and dislodge the
queen this is plus five already so it
gets bad really really quickly in any
case our opponent goes F6 and we switch
gears here we just grab the pawn on F6
maybe not the best move but definitely
the simplest approach to the position
and we switch from attacking the C4 Pawn
to attacking the more relevant weakness
which is of course E6 because that's the
pawn which is standing between R pieces
and Black's King
now King F7 is clearly a decisive
mistake and after Knight G5 check King
E7 loses immediately it accelerates the
process King G8 would have allowed black
to stay in the game for a bit longer
here we would have taken on E6 with the
Knight and on the next move we can
switch back to our old idea we can go
Queen E2 and win the pawn on C4 so this
is obviously a totally indefensible
position for black it's around plus four
but perhaps black can hold on here I
don't know
the engine suggest H5 that tells you all
you need to know about this position
Rick Gava asks could we go Queenie 2
instead of rookie one absolutely and I
even pointed this out the reason I
rejected Queen E2 is because I didn't
want to deal with the complications
after Knight takes D4
and to reiterate the line that I
presented during the game this position
I was not entirely sure how to evaluate
because as winning as it looks for white
there is only one piece in the attack
it's the queen so with the engine on I
see that white is in fact completely
winning but not with Queen C6 check this
would be a very Hasty move
notice that after King F7 the Rooks are
connected and white loses the attack the
move is actually just rookie one simple
chess attack the bishop on E7
Force The Black Queen to return to D7
and what has been the consequence of
that well now the C4 Pawn is finally
unprotected we could grab it and on the
next move Bishop A3 is going to create
devastating threats against Black's
Bishop on E7
okay
um and notice that black also can't
castle that's a very important function
of keeping the queen on this diagonal
so in any case that this was winning but
we decided to play it even simpler with
rookie one perhaps black should have
played a move like Knight d8 to at least
try to cling to this Pawn on E6 but my
idea here was just to go C3 and revert
back to our initial idea Bishop B7 just
go Knight bd2 at least here blackened
castle and the game continues at least
here the game continues but with an
extra Pawn Black's position is in
shambles the pawn on E6 is a terrible
weakness we've got a beautiful Pawn
chain on the queen side this is around
plus three so the game goes on but white
is obviously technically winning
so a simple game nothing nothing special
but nonetheless I think a good
illustration of basic ideas and I'm not
commentating past this point this is all
very obvious I think a good illustration
of uh nice play with a close Center
typical ideas in the NIMS of a trench
which is the first time that we Face the
French was this game and takeaways
involve ideas of attacking what may seem
to be an imposing Pawn chain on the
queen side so it's not always about how
much space your opponent controls it's
also about how well defended the pawn
chain is and you can use your Pawns in
many cases to what I would say what I
would call clear the strawberry just
like blast through
but what seems to be an imposing Pawn
chain and as a consequence of that you
often leave your opponent with just a
jumble of weaknesses that you can then
attack and the most common way of doing
that is by pushing B3 and then pushing
A4 and very importantly if you're on the
black side of a position like this make
sure that the Rook on A8 is protected so
that you can push A6 and at least
support the pawn on B5
all right
so that's what I'll say folks I would
get another game in but um I think it's
getting pretty late
I have lost in a speedrun but it's only
been to cheaters okay
[Music]